<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dagonizing of Bartholomew Fayre, caused through the Lord Majors command, for the battering downe the vanities of the gentiles, comprehended in flag and pole, appertayning to puppet-play.  The 23. of August being the day before the apostolicke fayre.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551101</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64551101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08886)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2864:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dagonizing of Bartholomew Fayre, caused through the Lord Majors command, for the battering downe the vanities of the gentiles, comprehended in flag and pole, appertayning to puppet-play.  The 23. of August being the day before the apostolicke fayre.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with Wing C4331: The cities loyaltie to their King. [London : s.n., 1647].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bartholomew Fair --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bartholomew Fair --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:184474:1"/>
            <head>The Dagonizing of <hi>Bartholomew Fayre,</hi> cauſed through the Lord Majors Command, for the battering downe the vanities of the Gentiles, comprehended in Flag and Pole, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to Puppet play.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 23. of Auguſt being the day before the Apoſtolicke Fayre.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>ON Auguſt's foure and twentieth Eve,</l>
               <l>The Cities Soveraigne and the Shrieve</l>
               <l>To Smithfield came if you'l beleeve to ſee th'ungodly flagges.</l>
               <l>The Livery men were ſore put too't,</l>
               <l>Though ſome wore ſhoe, and ſome wore boot,</l>
               <l>They 'wre all conſtraind to trans on foot,</l>
               <l>God ſave 'em.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Entring through Duck-lane at the Crowne,</l>
               <l>The ſoveraigne Cit began to frowne,</l>
               <l>As if 't abated his renowne, the paint did ſo o'retop him.</l>
               <l>Downe with theſe Dagons then, quoth he,</l>
               <l>They outbrave my dayes Regality,</l>
               <l>For's pride and partiality</l>
               <l>Jove crop him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile have no puppet-playes, quoth he,</l>
               <l>The harmleſſe-mirth diſpleaſeth me,</l>
               <l>Begun on Auguſt twenty three, 'tis full twelve howres too early.</l>
               <l>A Yonker then began to laugh,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt whom the Major advanc't white ſtaffe,</l>
               <l>And ſent him to the Compter ſafe,</l>
               <l>ſans parly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Another wight (in wofull wiſe)</l>
               <l>Beſought the Major, his pupetries,</l>
               <l>That he would not Babell-onize, ſurely they were not whoriſh.</l>
               <l>Oh do'nt my bratts Iſabellize,</l>
               <l>They ne're did Meretritialize</l>
               <l>Betwixt your Lordſhips Ladies thighes,</l>
               <l>peace Villaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Another Mortall had a clout,</l>
               <l>Which on a long pole did hang out,</l>
               <l>At which the Major turnd up his ſnout, for he was then advancing.</l>
               <l>Mounted with him came both the Shrieves,</l>
               <l>And Catchpoles with their hanging ſlieves,</l>
               <l>They ſhew'd much like a den of theev's</l>
               <l>though prauncing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that my Lord did ſilence breake,</l>
               <l>He op'd his mouth and thus did ſpeake,</l>
               <l>Tis fitteſt quoth he that the weake unto the walls ſhould goe.</l>
               <l>There was a Varlet (cloſe at hand)</l>
               <l>To execute (Gold chaines) command</l>
               <l>Pull'd wight away ſtraight, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </l>
               <l>ing, fowle twas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that ſhew'd wonders made of waxe,</l>
               <l>Spoke in behalfe of his fine knacks,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, we ſpit no fire of flax, nor ſuch like puppet ſhowes.</l>
               <l>Beſides we ſhew his Excellence,</l>
               <l>Quoth Major, that is a faire pretence,</l>
               <l>Gods-nigs tis time that I were hence</l>
               <l>s' away 'h goes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On top of Booth ſat pudding Iohn,</l>
               <l>(Lord would be loath to ſit thereon,)</l>
               <l>I'me ſure he wiſht his Lordſhip gone, yet durſt not tell him ſo.</l>
               <l>But when his Lordſhip left the Fayre,</l>
               <l>John ſet up throat did rend the Ayre,</l>
               <l>And glad he was, he lowd did ſweare</l>
               <l>he was gone.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>So was Mr. <hi>FINIS.</hi>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
